Finding Aid for Deane Baker papers, 1945-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Deane Baker papers 1945-2004, 1972-1996
Baker, Deane.
1 oversize folder
18 linear feet
2008039 Aa 2 Ac
Ann Arbor, Michigan businessman, Republican Regent of the University of Michigan, 1972-1996, candidate for office of United States Senator, 1976 and 1982. The collection includes Campaign and Political Files, 1964-1998, Personal Files, 1945-2004, Regental Files, 1975-1996, Photographs, and University of Michigan Presidential Search Files, 1978-1996.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library in June, 2007 by Deane Baker (donor no. 9902 ). Additional records were received in 2011
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection as a whole is restricted subject to university policy on executive records and some folders for attorney-client privileged communications which have been removed from the files and are closed to research.
The Vice President and Chief Financial Officer records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Dean Baker papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 1-18
Patient/Client Records -- Box 15
The client records have been removed to the vault.
Deane Baker was born in Marquette, Michigan on April 29, 1925. As a young man he completed two stints in the Air Force, from 1943 to 1945 and 1951-1953. Between these two periods of military service he completed his Bachelors degree in Business Administration at the University of Wisconsin in 1949 and married Marilyn Jane Hesse in 1951. After he completed his military service Baker entered the M.B.A. program at Harvard University, graduating in 1955.
After serving as the president of the Detroit-based H.F. Campbell Company and its subsidiaries, Baker founded the Deane Baker Company (later Ann Arbor Group, Inc.), a commercial and residential development and real estate firm.
In addition to his business interests and pursuits, Baker became active in state Republican Party politics in the 1960s, serving as a member of the Michigan for Milliken committee, and heading the Milliken campaign committee in Michigan's Second Congressional District. He also served as the Vice-Chairman of both the Washtenaw County and Scio Township Republican Parties, served on numerous political committees, and attended a number of State Republican conventions. Governor William Milliken appointed Baker to the Grand Valley State University Board of Control, on which Baker served from 1969-1972. In addition to his involvement in local politics, Baker ran unsuccessfully for the US Senate in 1976 and 1982.
In 1970 Baker unsuccessfully ran for a spot on the University of Michigan Board of Regents, the main governing body of the University. Though he failed to win his party's nomination in 1970, he did win his 1972 bid, beginning his 24-year tenure as a University Regent. In his time as Regent, Baker proved to be one of the most active, and also controversial members of the board, providing a dissenting conservative voice on the overwhelmingly Democratic board. He was involved in the selection of three University presidents, and helped to lead the University through major shifts in University operation and policy, such as the drafting of a new sexual orientation and discrimination policy, the decision as to whether to divest stock holdings with businesses doing business in South Africa before the fall of Apartheid, and the construction of the new University replacement hospital complex.
In addition to his business and political interests, Deane Baker was recognized for his religious and civic engagement and activities. He received Businessman of the Year Award, construction category, from Religious Heritage of America; received Business citizenship Award from Business Week magazine; Board of Directors Economic Club of Detroit and Laymen's National Bible Committee; he was an Elder in the First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor; a former director of Detroit Chamber of Commerce, Employers Association of Detroit, Detroit Rotary Club, Ann Arbor Senior Citizens Guild, Detroit Urban League; trustee, Historical Society of Michigan; former President Laymen's National Bible Committee; twice president Detroit Urban League. He and his wife Marilyn had three daughters Jamie, Wendy, Betsy; and one son, John.
The Deane Baker collection consists primarily of documentation of his campaigns for political office and his service as Regent of the University of Michigan. As the Bentley Library has a separate collection of Board of Regents records, the focus of the Deane Baker collection has been in those areas of university policy, procedure, and programs of most concern to him. The researcher is directed to the files of the Board of Regents and administrative offices of the university for the fullest description of Board of Regents history during the Baker years. Other portions of the collection relate to his various campaigns for public office. There is also a sampling of his other business and personal activities.
Subjects:
Baker, Deane.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1982.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Campaign and Political Files
  The Campaign and Political Files series contains correspondence, reports, and press clippings related to Baker's political activities and his own campaign records. This series includes campaign records from all of his runs for the University of Michigan Board of Regents, as well as from his two unsuccessful attempts at procuring a seat in the United States Senate in 1976 and 1982. Additionally, this series includes correspondence and other material related to his participation in the Michigan Republican Party as well as in his colleagues' campaigns.
  - 1964 (Box 1)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2032 ]
  - 1966 Republican Senate Nomination (Box 1)
  - 1968 Nixon Campaign (Box 1)
  - 1970 Regent Candidacy (Box 1)
  - 1972 Regent Campaign
    - Campaign (Box 1)
    - Contributions/Thank You Letters (Box 1)
    - Letters (Box 1)
    - Letters of Congratulations (Box 1)
    - Republican Nomination (Box 1)
    - Press Clippings (Box 1)
    - Scheduling (Box 1)
  - 1976 Senate Campaign
    - Senate Campaign (Box 1)
    - Senate Campaign Clippings, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Senate Campaign Clippings (cont.) (Box 2)
  - 1980 Regent Reelection Campaign
    - Regent Reelection Campaign, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Special Interest Groups Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Press Clippings (Box 2)
  - 1982 Senate Campaign
    - Senate Campaign (Box 2)
    - Senate Campaign Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Planning and Exploratory Committee (Box 2)
    - Political Events (Box 2)
  - 1988 Regent Reelection
    - Campaign Finance (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Convention (Box 2)
      - College Republicans (Box 2)
      - Letters of Congratulations (Box 2)
      - Letters and Personal Thank Yous (Box 2)
      - Lindemer, Larry (Box 2)
      - Pursell, Carl (Box 3)
      - Thank Yous and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Fund Raising (Box 3)
    - News Releases (Box 3)
    - Post-Convention Press Clips (Box 3)
    - Press Clippings and Releases, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Official Election Returns (Box 3)
    - Questionnaires (Box 3)
  - 1990
    - Gubernatorial Election, Campaign Support (Box 3)
  - 1992-1994
    - Political Correspondence (Box 3)
  - 1994 Regent Race
    - Alumni Involvement (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Fisher, Andrea (Box 3)
    - Smith Campaign (Box 3)
  - 1996 Regent Reelection
    - Campaign Finance Reports (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Department of State Reports (post-election) (Box 3)
    - Endorsements (Box 3)
    - Support Cards (Box 3)
  - 1998 Regent Reelection
    - Endorsements (Box 3)
    - Post-Election Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Republican Events and Correspondence (Box 3)
- Personal Files 1945-2004
  The Personal Files series contains biographical information, personal correspondence, files related to Baker's active participation as an Elder in the First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor, service with the Air Force, and correspondence related to Baker's role as the president and founder of the Ann Arbor Group, a development and realty company based in Ann Arbor.
  - Biography (Box 3)
  - Air War College Thesis (Box 3)
  - Certificates (Outsize) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1967-1972, 1976, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979-1987, 2003-2004, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - Deane Baker Scholarship 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - John Deane Baker 2004 (Box 4)
  - European Tour 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Presbyterian Church Activities 1970-1972, 1978-2002 (Box 4)
  - Hazel Littlefield Smith 1979-1982 (Box 4)
  - Yankee Air Force 2003 (Box 4)
- Regental Files
  The Regental Files series contains correspondence, meeting notes, and other materials related to Baker's tenure as Regent of the University of Michigan. These files are organized by date, but within the chronological structure Baker maintained certain topical files on major issues facing the board such as South African divestment and files related to the construction of a new university hospital. Baker kept copies of his incoming and outgoing correspondence, making the correspondence files of this series particularly rich. Additional content relating to the university's sexual orientation policies is in a separate series University of Michigan Bylaw 14.06 (Nondiscrimination policy).
  - 1975
    - Jewell Cobb Tenure Controversy (Box 5)
    - PIRGIM 1975-1978 (Box 5)
    - Trip to Warsaw, Moscow, Cairo, Athens, Jerusalem, Rome (Box 5)
  - 1976
    - China Trip, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1977
    - China Trip, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Schreimer, Christine (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan Hospital 1977-1981 (Box 5)
  - 1978
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) Rehabilitation Act Compliance (Box 5)
    - Office for Civil Rights (OCR)/ HEW Agreement Files (Box 5)
    - OCR/HEW Clippings (Box 5)
    - South Africa Divestment (Box 5)
    - South Africa Clippings (Box 5)
  - 1979
    - Art Festival (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - South Africa (Box 5)
    - University Hospital (Box 5)
  - 1980
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Stegeman/Quadrium Complex, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Salaries (Box 6)
  - 1981
    - Brickley Amendment (regarding the appointment vs. election of regents (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Real Estate Program (Box 6)
    - Replacement Hospital Project (Box 6)
  - 1982
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - PIRGIM (Box 6)
    - Residence Halls (Box 6)
  - 1983
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Military Research (Box 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7)
    - PIRGIM (Box 7)
    - Sexual Orientation Policy (Box 7)
    - South Africa, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1984
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Play (Box 7)
    - Proposal C (Box 7)
    - Replacement Hospital (Box 7)
    - Replacement Hospital Program Reports (Box 7)
    - Sexual Orientation Policy (Box 7)
    - Telecommunications Project (Box 7)
  - 1985
    - Correspondence, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Alumnus Perspective, "In Defense of Freedom" (Box 8)
    - Minority Students (Box 8)
    - Naval ROTC (Box 8)
    - PIRGIM (Box 8)
    - SDI (Strategic Defense Initiative) Research Debate, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Tuition Increase (Box 8)
  - 1986
    - Correspondence, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - PIRGIM, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Regents (Box 9)
    - Replacement Hospital (Box 9)
    - Reserve Officers Training Corp (ROTC) Remarks (Box 9)
  - 1987
    - Correspondence, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Black Action Movement (Box 9)
    - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Editorials-Racism at Michigan (Box 9)
    - PIRGIM, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Policy on Sexual Orientation (Box 9)
    - South Africa (Nelson Mandela Honorary Degree) (Box 9)
    - Weapons Research (Box 9)
  - 1988
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Academic Freedom (Jeane J. Kirkpatrick) (Box 10)
    - School of Dentistry (Box 10)
    - Washtenaw and Forest Property (Box 10)
  - 1989
    - Access by Federal Agencies to Recruit (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment Policy (U of M) (Box 10)
    - Michigan Daily (Box 10)
    - Political Correctness (Box 10)
    - Speeches (Box 10)
    - Verbatim Remarks at Regents Meetings (Box 10)
  - 1990
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (cont.) (Box 11)
    - Apology to Faculty (Davis, Nickerson, Markert) fired in the 1950s (Box 11)
    - Michigan Review Interview (Box 11)
    - Political Correctness (Box 11)
    - President's Advisory Group (Box 11)
    - Rights and Responsibilities Statement Draft (Box 11)
  - 1991
    - Correspondence, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - George Bush Commencement (Box 11)
    - Cancelled Regents Meeting (Box 11)
    - Discrimination and Discriminatory Conduct (Box 11)
    - HHS Audit (Box 11)
    - Political Correctness (Box 12)
    - Political Correctness Clippings (Box 12)
    - Relation with President and Regents (Box 12)
    - Sexual Harassment Policy (Box 12)
    - WCBN (Obscenity Complaint) (Box 12)
  - 1992
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Anne Duderstadt Employment (Box 12)
    - Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment Policy (Box 12)
    - Michigan Collegiate Coalition (Box 12)
    - Notes (Box 12)
    - Political Correctness (Box 12)
    - Speech Code (Box 12)
    - Speech Code Clippings (Box 12)
    - Statement of Student Rights and Responsibilities (proposed) (Box 12)
    - Warner-Lambert Land Sale (Box 12)
  - 1993
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Athletic Director Search, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Department of Population Planning and International Health (Box 12)
    - Executive Compensation (Box 12)
    - Mack, Charlie (Box 12)
    - Michigan Daily (Box 12)
  - 1994
    - General (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Alumni and Community Members (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, College Republicans (Box 13)
    - Defense and Indemnification of Regents (Box 13)
    - Michigan Agenda for Women (Box 13)
  - 1995
    - General (Box 13)
    - Clippings (Box 13)
    - Selection of New Provost (Box 13)
    - Student Rights and Responsibilities (Speech Code) (Box 13)
    - Student Rights and Responsibilities Clippings (Box 13)
  - 1996
    - General (Box 13)
    - Cohen, Carl (Box 13)
    - Medical Center, Possible Restructuring (Box 13)
    - Neal, Homer (Interim President) (Box 13)
    - Undisclosed Employment Agreements (Box 13)
    - Last Meeting and Retirement Celebration 1996-1997 (Box 13)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series relates to his political campaigns and to various university events and activities. Of note are photographs of President George H. W. Bush when he gave the commencement address at the University of Michigan in 1991.
  - Campaign Photos (Box 13)
  - Regental Photos
    - 1978-1988 (Box 13)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 13)
  - George H.W. Bush 1991 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 13)
- University of Michigan Presidential Search Files
  Deane Baker was involved in the selection of three presidents of the University of Michigan: Harold Shapiro, James Duderstadt, and Lee Bollinger. The files related to these presidential searches comprise the University of Michigan Presidential Search Files series. This series includes correspondence, committee reports, interview notes, as well as notes and documents relating to a lawsuit relating to an alleged violation of Michigan's Open Meetings Act during the 1987/1988 presidential search.
  - 1978
    - Presidential Selection Committee Report (Box 14)
    - Search Files, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - 1987-1988
    - Presidential Search Files, General, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Pre-Search Interview Files, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Committee Files, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Open Meeting Act/Freedom of Information Requests re. 1987/1988 Search, 1994-1995
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2088 ]
  - 1996
    - Presidential Search Files, 2 folders
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2088; removed to vault]
- University of Michigan Bylaw 14.06 (Non-discrimination policy)
  The series University of Michigan Bylaw 14.06 (Nondiscrimination policy) contains documentation on controversies on campus in the early to mid-1990s surrounding sexual orientation, particularly the amendment of Regents Bylaw 14.06 (Nondiscrimination) in 1993-94 to include non-discrimination based on sexual orientation. Baker's outspoken conservative position opposing the bylaw amendment made him a lightning rod in the debates. Baker's files richly illustrate the divisive nature of these debates as the files contain material from supporters and detractors. The files include newspaper clippings, correspondence, petitions sent to Regents, and background articles on gay issues and homosexuality. Material from other gay rights issues in the early 1990s is also included relating to counseling services offered by the Lesbian-Gay Male Program Office (LGMPO) and efforts to change the definition of family as it related to University of Michigan Family Housing in 1991. The organization ACT-UP staged a protest at Baker's residence in 1990. Clippings and material relating to the protest is also included.
  - Bylaws Committee 1993 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence (Box 16)
  - Letters (Box 16)
  - Mailing List (Box 16)
  - Media Releases 1994 (Box 16)
  - News Clippings circa 1990-1994, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - News Summaries (Box 16)
  - Notes (Box 16)
  - Petitions (Box 16)
  - Statements by Deane Baker 1994 (Box 16)
  - Regents Meeting September 1993 (Box 16)
  - Regents Meeting April-May, 1994 (Box 16)
  - UM 14.06 Related
  - Gay Issues
    - General (Box 17)
    - ACT-UP Protest at Baker's Residence 1990 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence (re: homosexuality) 1990-1991, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Gays (articles and clippings) (Box 17)
    - "Homophobia" Course 1994 (Box 17)
    - Lesbian and Gay Male (LGM) Program Office 1990-1991 (Box 17)
- Book Project
  The Book Project series contains proposals, notes and background material from an unrealized project to write a monograph about university policy making from an insider's perspective. The files contain chapter outlines and some brief summaries. The material is organized as it was maintained by Baker, reflecting a scheme he devised to match his proposed chapters. Files include background source material such as clippings, statements, and correspondence. Topics include Baker's relations with various University of Michigan presidents, other regents, and significant topics such as speech codes, political correctness, sexual orientation and affirmative action.
  - Book Project Files, 45 folders (Box 17)
- Audio Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual series contains a scattering of audio recordings and videotapes in a variety of formats. Audio recording include a 1980 campaign radio spot and various recordings of Board of Regents meetings from 1984 to 1996. Videotapes include programs where Baker was a panelist or commentator ranging from a program on nuclear disarmament to campus demonstrations over campus police and homosexuality.
  - Audio Material
    - Audio cassette recordings 1984-1996 (primarily Regents Meetings) (Box 18)
    - 1980 Radio Spot, reel-to-reel (Box 18)
  - Video Material
    - "A Thoughtful Discussion of Political Correctness and Academic Values (University of Michigan Faculty and Regents)," October 21, 1993 (Box 18)
    - "Baker", VHS (Box 18)
    - Bill Bonds Channel 7 Interview (Campus Police Force and Homosexual Rights Demonstration), Beta SP (Box 18)
    - "Capitol Close-Up" Nuclear Disarmament (Perry Bullard, host, Deane Baker and Irwin Gaede) June 25, 1982, U-matic (Box 18)
    - "Spotlight 1885" June 12, 1982, U-matic (Box 18)